<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Scandinavian PhD Seminar</title>
    <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Scandinavian PhD Seminar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Demand for Signalling”, Jonas Lundstedt</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-20/</guid>
      <description>In this paper, I study how students in higher education react to an opportunity to manipulate from which university they will receive a diploma upon finishing their bachelors degree. On January 1st 2010 two Swedish higher educational institutions: Kalmar University College and Växjö University merged and became Linnaeus University. Using data on the population of Swedish university students, I exploit that this merger provided some students with the opportunity to change their signal (the diploma) while keeping their human capital (the education) constant by adjusting their graduation date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Credit Shocks and Populism”, Alessandro Pizzigolotto</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-19/</guid>
      <description>Do banking crises fuel populism? While scholars identified the economic causes of populism in trade, unemployment, or migration, the evidence on the role of banks is scant. In this paper we aim to fill this gap. We investigate whether lending cuts by banks increase the electoral support for populist parties. To this end, we exploit the impact of an exogenous lending cut by a large German bank in 2007-08 on the voting behaviour of individuals set in counties exposed to the cut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Rank Effects and Skill Formation”, Alexander Fischer</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-18/</guid>
      <description>Why does a higher class rank in school translate into improved achievement throughout adolescence? Leveraging Danish administrative data and a population-wide survey, this paper shows that a student’s class rank at age 8 improves test scores throughout adolescence up to high-school. The improvements in academic achievement are accompanied by increased non-cognitive skills and higher academic self-perception. Students with higher class rank further report better relationships to their teachers, but no improvements in well-being.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Sibling Gender, Inheritance Norms and Human Capital Formation in Sub-Saharan Africa”, Matthew Collins</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-17/</guid>
      <description>I study how sibling gender, a central part of the childhood experience, affects the educational outcomes of children across 36 Sub-Saharan African countries. Using data from the Demographic and Health Survey, I estimate the causal effect of having a next-born brother relative to a sister and how it varies across ethnic groups according to inheritance norms. Girls experience a small negative effect of having a brother. In both patrilineal and matrilineal societies, male property is inherited by other male heirs, but specifically who inherits the property varies by kinship, with sons directly inheriting their father’s property in most patrilineal societies, while in matrilineal societies, property is generally transferred to the son (or sons) of a man’s sister.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Job Loss and Domestic Violence: Evidence from Denmark”, Anne Sophie Lassen</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-16/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-16/</guid>
      <description>In this study, we investigate the effect of job loss on couple dynamics and domestic violence. By using employer-employee linked data from Denmark, we identify plant closures that were exogenous to the workers to apply an event-study design. We focus on sectors where plant closure lead to substantial unemployment and investigate the changes in relationship status and risk of domestic violence. We find gender differences in changes in relationship status after job loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Fertility, Family Formation and Human Capital&#34;, Eirik Berger</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-15/</guid>
      <description>By varying the intensity of compulsory schooling while keeping the number of compulsory school years constant, this paper generates new insights into the effect of human capital on fertility on the extensive and intensive margin. We leverage population-wide panel data for Norway in combination with a school reform in the 1930s changing the instruction time during the school year that allows us to isolate the effect of human capital investment on fertility behavior across the life-cycle from an incarceration effect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;How Valuable Are Business Networks? Evidence from Salesmen in Internatoinal Goods Markets&#34;, Bérengère Patault</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-14/</guid>
      <description>How to gain new buyers and expand one’s business? This paper provides a very simple answer to this question: by hiring salesmen. Combining French firm-to-firm trade data with a detailed occupational dataset, we offer new empirical evidence that salesmen play a role for the construction of a firm’s portfolio of foreign buyers. We then characterize a specific channel explaining such a role: using an event-study design, we show that a poached salesman brings on average 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Revealing Equity Principles from Tax Policy&#34;, Kristoffer Berg</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-13/</guid>
      <description>Which equity principles can support current tax policy? This paper shows how vertical and horizontal equity rationalize tax policy choices by governments. While vertical equity provides the standard inequality aversion rationale for redistributive taxation, most tax models ignore horizontal equity. Horizontal equity introduces a restriction against tax discrimination based on certain characteristics, which is necessary to explain current tax policy. The first contribution is to map the government’s total marginal priority into the concerns for vertical and horizontal equity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Export Shocks and Firm Competition&#34;, Simone Maria Bonin</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-12/</guid>
      <description>Are export shocks transmitted between firms competing in the same labour market? In particular, how does labour market competition affect firms and workers that are exposed to successful exporters? To answer these questions, we employ administrative linked employer-employee dataset covering the population of Danish firms and workers, a novel approach to define labour markets through clustered worker transitions between jobs, and an empirical strategy based on shocks to firm-level export stemming from variation in World Import Demand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Child Care and Later-In-Life Delinquency&#34;, Mirjam Wentzel</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-11/</guid>
      <description>Formal child care has proven to affect long-term outcomes, such as education, income and health, but does it also change the risk of later-in-life delinquency? In this paper, I investigate how formal child care affects criminal charges in youth or adulthood. I use multiple reforms connected to formal child care in Norway, together with rich Norwegian register data, identifying differential access or incentives to use formal child care. I find that formal child care can decrease the likelihood of being charged, driven by men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Gender Peer Composition and Labour Market Outcomes&#34;, Demid Getik</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-10/</guid>
      <description>This Seminar will start 15 minutes later than usual (12:30 to 13:30).
We examine how the gender composition in compulsory school affects gender gaps in subsequent labour-market outcomes. For identification, we rely on Swedish administrative data and cohort variation in peer gender within schools. We find that an increase in the share of girls improves girls&#39; wages and diminishes the gap in both actual and potential earnings. There appear to be no significant effects on boys&#39; labour-market outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Early Schooling and Maternal Labour Market Outcomes: Evidence from a New School Entry Policy Using Exact Date of Birth in Brazil&#34;, Daniel Duque</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-9/</guid>
      <description>This paper aims to use a national age-at-school-entry policy to identify the causal effect of mothers getting their children enrolled a year earlier in Primary School. Brazilian public and private primary schools admit children up to one year younger than the national minimum age to enter school if their birthday is before an arbitrary threshold, defined as March 31. Using a Fuzzy Regression Discontinuity Design and a Fixed-Effects Event-Study, we estimate the impact of having children enrolled in Primary School on mothers’ labor outcomes, using longitudinal data from a quarterly Brazilian socioeconomic survey.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Heterogeneous Employment Effects of Firms Financial Constraints and Wageless Recoveries&#34;, Gabriel Züllig</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-8/</guid>
      <description>This paper studies the interaction of firm liquidity, employment and wages in light of credit supply disruptions. I establish that firms borrowing from banks highly exposed to the money-market freeze during the Global Financial Crisis received a shock to external liquidity, relative to otherwise similar firms. This constraint led to a significant drop in employment in affected firms, while wages did not fall relative to unaffected firms. In order to retain cash flow and build up internal liquidity, constrained firms cut labor cost predominantly by changing the composition of their labor force in favor of workers with lower wages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Earnings and Labor Market Dynamics: Predicting Macro Dynamics using Micro Data&#34;, Johan Holmberg</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-7/</guid>
      <description>In this paper I build a life cycle earnings dynamics model including endogenous employment and job changes and estimate it with indirect inference using Swedish register data. By simulating data from this microeconomic model I study macroeconomic consequences of transitory shocks to unemployment risk. The results show that transitory aggregate shocks to unemployment risk have have long lasting negative effects on employment, income and earnings volatility. I also provide some insights on what effects unemployment at various stages during the working life has on the accumulation of pension entitlements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Return of the King The Effect of the Civil War in Greece on Female Labor Force Participation&#34;, Xanthi Tsoukli</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-6/</guid>
      <description>Using the civil war in Greece as an exogenous shock, this paper investigates the relationship between conflict and female labor force participation. The civil war in Greece was the result of a struggle between left and right ideologies. Exploiting a referendum that took place right before the outbreak of the civil war in 1946 regarding the return of the King, the paper shows that provinces with high concentration of communists experience a higher female labor force participation after the war.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Cultural Assimilation of Individualism and Preferences for Redistribution&#34;, Olle Hammar</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-5/</guid>
      <description>In this study, I analyze the relationship between individualism and preferences for income redistribution and equality, using variation in immigrants&#39; countries of origin to capture the impact of cultural beliefs on individual preferences. Using global survey data for a large number of individuals and countries around the world, I find strong support for the hypothesis that coming from a more individualistic culture is negatively and significantly associated with an individual&amp;rsquo;s preferences for redistribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Bill Complexity and Voting in the Danish Parliament&#34;, Martin Strobl</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-4/</guid>
      <description>For a version of the working paper please directly contact the author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Robots and Firms&#34;, Ilya Manyulov</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-3/</guid>
      <description>We study the implications of robot adoption at the level of individual firms using a rich panel data-set of Spanish manufacturing firms over a 27-year period (1990-2016). We focus on three central questions: (1) Which firms adopt robots? (2) What are the labor market effects of robot adoption at the firm level? (3) How does firm heterogeneity in robot adoption affect the industry equilibrium? To address these questions, we look at our data through the lens of recent attempts in the literature to formalize the implications of robot technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Effects of More Informative Grading in Early Schooling: Evidence from Sweden&#34;, Matthew Collins</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-2/</guid>
      <description>It is well established that education has a significant effect on earnings. Moreover, academic skills have been shown to determine a host of non-pecuniary benefits. The imparting of academic skills and human capital can be increased if inputs in education production are used more efficiently. One such input is the provision of performance feedback. Using data on the population of Swedish school children, we identify a natural experiment arising from a reform to the grading system in compulsory school which introduced a more granular grading scale and thus provided students with more informative feedback on their performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;The Cost of Terrorism: Network Effects and the Economic Impact of Child Loss&#34;, Ragnar Alne and Nina Serdarevic</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/post/seminar-1/</guid>
      <description>Using a difference-in-differences model on full population data, we estimate the causal effects of a terrorist attack on labor market and social insurance outcomes of bereaved parents. Compared with non-bereaved parents, we find substantial negative effects. One mechanism through which these changes occur is impaired psychological health. This result is consistent with theoretical and empirical work emphasizing the connection between adverse health shocks and labor market outcomes. Moreover, the results suggest that the cost of terrorism and the value of preventive measures may be underestimated if negative spillover effects to the victims’ family network remain unrecognized.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://scand-phdseminar.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>Please contact us via e-mail if you wish to attend or present at the seminar. If you wish to present please send along a copy of your paper or long abstract
 Alexander Fischer - Aarhus University René Karadakic - Norwegian School of Economics  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
